Belachew "Billy" Haile-Mariam

Java Wizard | DevOps Ninja | Automation Enthusiast

Full-Stack Software Engineer with 3+ years of experience in the corporate financial sector. My technical background is versatile, and includes experience in Java, Web Development, DevOps, Automation, and Containerization. I excel in fast-paced environments, and have been successful leading team projects. I enjoy learning new things on the spot—it keeps life interesting!

Technical Skills

- Programming Languages: Java, Spring, Python, JavaScript, C/C#, Groovy
- Web Development: Spring Boot, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, ¡Query, AngularJS
- Creating and interacting with SOAP and RESTful web services
- Source Code Management: Git/SourceTree, Subversion/TortiseSVN
- DevOps/Release Engineering: Jenkins, uDeploy, Maven, Nexus/Artifactory
- Test Automation: Selenium, Cucumber, HP Unified Functional Testing
- Platform/Infrastructure Automation: Docker, Vagrant, Chocolatey, VMware, VirtualBox
- Relational and Non-Relational Databases: SQL, Splunk, Cassandra, Teradata



Experience

Software Engineer at Capital One

Home Loans Servicing, April 2017 – Present

Software Engineering

- Designed and implemented a testing solution that involved wrapping a Spring Boot application around existing Selenium/Cucumber test automation, and exposing it as a set of RESTful web services and a custom SwaggerUI interface. The application was then Dockerized, and deployed to AWS for start of day production validations, infrastructure rehydrations, and L3 production support application monitoring
- Refactored and added new features to an internal application that tracks the progress of home loans as they move from the originations to servicing department. Angular Front end with a Java/Spring Back end.
- Automated a manual internal audit process using Java, Splunk, and SQL. Splunk logs from our online portal were crossreferenced with loan boarding data to validate that only customers who clicked an "I accept" button on our terms and
 conditions page were enrolled in recurring payments. A PDF report was then generated outlining every loan that either
 passed or failed the audit

Production Support

• Supporting production deployments, testing/validating infrastructure rehydrations, and resolving customer digital escalations

DevOps

- Migrated Jenkins build jobs from an on-prem Jenkins 1.x instance to a Jenkins 2.x instance running on AWS
- Utilized GitHub, Jenkins, and cURL to automate part of our QA and Production deployments to AWS

Software Engineer at Fidelity Investments

Fidelity Pricing and Cash Management Services, January 2017 – Mar 2017 (3 months)

DevOps

- Reverse engineered a Java web application from a WAR file (created through an Ant build) into a mult-module Maven project, while simultaneously migrating the application from Subversion to Git. This shrunk the size of the code base down from over 4 GB to approximately 45 MB, and greatly improved the consistency and build time of each CI/CD build
- Created Batch scripts that utilize Chocolatey to automatically download, install, and configure software on Windows machines
- Installed Jenkins slave agents to run on virtual Windows machines, and configured them to be resilient and stay online as much as possible

Test Automation

- Migrated over 50 test automation source code repositories from SVN to Git, and renamed each project to follow a consistent naming convention to make them more easily identifiable
- Introduced the Allure Reporting Framework to my team, which provided a consistent way to showcase test results and test metrics
- Created a Maven project that defined clear and specific build goals for compilation, testing, packaging, installation, deployment, and reporting. This was then used as a parent project to all our other maven test automation projects, which provided my team with clean and consistent automated tests and reporting

Associate Software Engineer at Fidelity Investments

Fidelity Pricing and Cash Management Services, August 2015 – January 2017 (1 year 6 months)

DevOps

- Developed a migration strategy to move development teams and their code repositories from Subversion to Git
- Facilitated training sessions to teach source control concepts using Git, Stash, SourceTree, and different development workflows (Central Repository, Feature Branches, Gitflow)
- Onboarded new and existing applications to CI/CD Jenkins pipelines, and modified existing pipelines as needed
- Improved a DevOps dashboard to showcase code coverage, deployment metrics, and application compliance

Test Automation

- Worked in a development team to create and maintain a library of common test automation functions in Java
- Migrated Java applications from Ant to Maven, and moved artifacts out of source control repositories into artifact repositories (Nexus, Artifactory)
- Converted manual test cases into automated tests, and incorporated them into existing CI/CD pipelines

Associate Software Engineer at Fidelity Investments

Leap Program, August 2015 – December 2015 (5 months)

- Completed Software Engineering training modules on Object-Oriented Analysis & Design, UNIX Essentials, Oracle 11g
 & Data Modeling, Big Data, Java/XML, The Spring Framework, Service Oriented Architecture, Developing Dynamic Web Applications, and C# Programming
- Developed a system for Fidelity's Asset Management division to import, normalize, and store data from credit rating agencies into Hadoop. This allowed the firm to find credit rating mismatches between that information and data imported from credit rating aggregation services, saving the company millions of dollars in liabilities

Technical Intern at Fidelity Investments

Fidelity Pricing and Cash Management Services, June 2014 – August 2014 (3 months)

- Tested RESTful web services with SoapUI to measure latency, find security vulnerabilities, and ensure appropriate responses
- Constructed a web dashboard to showcase project overviews and associated metrics
- Managed and updated an online catalog of the services created

Web Application Developer Intern at Ayoka Systems

June 2013 – May 2014 (1 year)

- Designed and built web applications using the Grails framework and MVC architecture
- Worked with an Agile team to gather customer requirements and performed testing to verify that specifications were met
- Modified existing applications based on customer needs

Education

The University of Texas at Arlington

Bachelor's Degree, Computer Engineering, 2010 - 2015

- Senior Design Project Leader, Team SmartGrass (September 2014 May 2015)
- Founding Father of the Theta-Omega Chapter of the Kappa Sigma Fraternity (November 2013 May 2015)